Guide to the J.H. McKnight and Company records 1865-1914
Montana Historical Society
J.H. McKnight and Company records
1865-1914
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 56
J.H. McKnight and Company
21 linear feet of shelf space
J.H. McKnight and Company operated as the post trader at Fort Shaw, Montana Territory, from 1870 to 1887. In 1887 Joseph McKnight moved his business to Great Falls, where it became a general mercantile firm. In 1894 the name was changed to J.H. McKnight Company, and it continued to operate under that name after McKnight's death in 1903 until its charter expired in 1914. Records (1865-1914) include interoffice, incoming, and outgoing correspondence; financial records; legal documents; and organizational materials.
J.H. McKnight and Company was founded by Joseph Hempstead McKnight during the years following 1870. McKnight, originally from Dubuque, Iowa, came west in the 1860s in the company of Thomas C. Power, a business associate. Before forming his own company, McKnight worked as clerk at sutler stores at Fort Buford, at Camp Cook on the Judith River, and at Fort Benton, where he arrived in August 1866. In 1871, McKnight, assisted by the financial backing of T.C. Power, took charge of the trading post at Fort Shaw, Montana. Fort Shaw, located at Sun River Crossing twenty miles above the mouth of the Sun River, was established in 1867. An infantry post, it served as the regimental headquarters in the military department of the Territory of Montana. It was designed to protect settlers and prospectors, to prevent the invasion of Blackfeet treaty land, and to keep the route between Fort Benton and the Helena gold fields open. As the licensed post trader, J.H. McKnight and Company served the military, plus trappers, area settlers, Indian agents from the Blackfeet Agency, and the Northwest Mounted Police of Canada. In its operation, J.H. McKnight and Company was very closely connected with T.C. Power and Brother at Fort Benton, the two owners being personal friends and business allies throughout McKnight's life. The firms supplied each other, shared orders, provided transportation for commodities, and conferred on the prices and availability of goods. In 1887, McKnight sold the Fort Shaw traders' post and moved his operation to Great Falls. There, J.H. McKnight and Company served as "wholesale and retail grocers and dealers in agricultural implements, wagons, harness, and building materials," at the corner of Central Avenue and Third Street in the McKnight Block. The organization of the firm was formalized in 1894 when bylaws were adopted, stock was issued, and the name was altered to J.H. McKnight Company. Originally there were only four stockholders: T.C. Power and J.H. McKnight (499 shares each) and F. George Heldt and C.B. Power (one share each). These men also served as the Company's Board of Trustees, alternating the offices of the Board among themselves. When McKnight died on January 20, 1903, the other three trustees continued the business until the expiration of the J.H. McKnight Company charter on June 4, 1914. At that time the corporation was dissolved and all company property was sold, with the assets of the firm totaling more than $108,000. This money was dispersed to the corporation's stockholders.
Content Description:
These records are primarily concerned with the basic daily operation of the McKnight business. The correspondence consists of orders directed to McKnight from soldiers and settlers of the Fort Shaw area and of transactions with various suppliers of the McKnight firm. The financial records consist of bills and statements, both with individuals and with supplying companies, and bound volumes including journals, ledgers, and cash books. The remainder of the material is composed of legal documents (including licenses, agreements, and contracts), and of materials relating to the formal organization of the J.H. McKnight Company, 1894-1914.
Arranged by series. Some material housed in the manuscript volumes. See inventory below for more information.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
McKnight, J. H. (Joseph Hempstead), -1903
J.H. McKnight and Company
Fort Benton (Mont.)--Commerce; Fort Shaw (Mont.)--Commerce; Fort Shaw (Mont.: Fort); Great Falls (Mont.)--Commerce
Blackfeet Indians--Trading posts; Military bases--Montana; Trading posts--Montana; General stores--Montana--Fort Shaw; General stores--Montana--Great Falls; Wagons
Montana; Business, Industry, and labor; Military
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Biographical Materials
  - J.H. McKnight obituary, 1903 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - J.H. McKnight, F. George Heldt, John Heldt, 1873-1874 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - J.H. McKnight & Co., Fort Benton (F. George Heldt) and J.H. McKnight & Co., Great Falls (J.H. McKnight), 1887-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Incoming Correspondence
  - Joseph W. Allen (Warner's Ranch), 1872 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Sister Mary Amadeus (St. Peter's Mission), 1886-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - S.C. Ashby (Helena), 1875-1887 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - John T. Athey (Sun River), 1885-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Charles Aubrey (Blackfeet Agency), 1874-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - A (correspondents include J.C. Adams, American Wine Company, Anheuser-Busch Brewing Association, J. Armitage, Anthony and Kuhn Brewing Company, F.E. Augustin, C.H. Austin, James W. Austin, J.W. Avery), 1872-1887 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - I.G. Baker and Company (Fort Benton), 1873-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Benton Transportation Company, 1887 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - John E. Blaine; James F. Blaine (Helena), 1876-1884 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Thomas J. Bogy (Fort McLeod, N.W.T.), 1873-1879 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Theodore and Marie Boll (Bird Tail), 1871-1874 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - J.R. Boyce and Company (Helena), 1873-1876 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - C.A. Broadwater and Company; Broadwater, McCulluh and Company, 1881-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - B (correspondents include Bach, Cory and Company; Bain Wagon Company; W.C. Bartlett; Frank Bartos; Best, Russell and Company; John Billing; Nathan F. Block; H.D. Blossom; J.V. Bogert; E.L. Bonner and Company; W.J. Boston; C.L. Bristol; George L. Browning; Frank Bull; W.P. Burcher), 1872-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 17-18)
  - Cameron, Amberg and Company (Chicago), 1886-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Clark Brothers and Company (Choteau), 1886-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Clarke, Conrad and Curtin (Helena), 1872-1874 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - T.A. Cummings and Company (Fort Benton), 1874-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - C (correspondents include E.W. Carpenter, Marie Carrothers, J.W. Carter, John K. Castner, W.K. Cate, W.C. Child, J. Choate, E. Dalrymple Clark, Horace Clark, Joseph Cobell, Robert Coburn, H.J. Coffroth, Charles E. Colbert, Tom Connolly, William Courtenay), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - D (correspondents include J. Damien, David Dannitt [?], Davis and Wallace, T.J. Demers, Detroit and Montana Cattle Company, John Devine, N.C. Draper, J.R. Drew, Thomas Dunn, John C. Duval), 1871-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - E (correspondents include Eddy, Harvey and Carter; C.F. Ellis and Company, William F. Ensign, W.R. Evans), 1872-1889 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - First National Bank of Helena, 1872-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 26-27)
  - Franklin MacVeagh and Company, 1881-1887 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - F (correspondents include W.F. Fanton, James Fergus, First National Bank of Fort Benton, Fish Brothers Wagon Company, Fisk and Van Uxum, M.A. Flanagan, J.H. Ford, R.S. Ford, Sam Ford, L. Cass Forsyth, Frankel and Block, Fred R. Frost), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Gans and Klein (Helena), 1872-1886 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Thomas Gorham (Dodge), 1873-1887 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - G (correspondents include William Gaddis, James Gibson, Paris Gibson, William W. Giddings, W.C. Gillette, S.P. Goin, F.S. Goss, Ike Greenhood), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - A.B. Hamilton; Hamilton and Hazlett (Sun River, Choteau), 1872-1886 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - F.F. Healy; J.J. Healy; William Healy (Sun River), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Joseph Hirshberg and Company (Choteau); Julius Hirshberg and Company (Sun River), 1887-1890 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - D.J. Hogan (South Fork, Sun River), 1872-1887 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - A.M. Holter and Brother; Holter Lumber Company, 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - S.L. Holtzman and Brother (Helena), 1872-1877 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - H (correspondents include R.S. Hale, S.M. Hall, A.C. Haptonstall, Elbert E. Hanchett, Edward Harper, R.B. Harrison, Oliver Hastzal, I.N. Hazlett, D.C. Holbrook, Q. Van Hummell, Ed L. Huntley), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - I-J (correspondents include C. Imoda, I.R. Jackson, Joy and Fitzpatrick), 1874-1890 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - H.A. Kennerly (Fort Maginnis), 1872-1879 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - John Kinna; Kinna and Jack (Helena), 1871-1887 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Nick Kessler; Kessler and Miller; Kessler's Brewery (Helena), 1873-1881 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - K (correspondents include J.A. Kanouse, John Keiplinger, Charles P. Kellogg and Company, F. Kendrick, Fred J. Kiesel and Company, Joseph Kipp, T.S. Kirtland), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - John Largent and Company; James M. Largent (Sun River), 1872-1887 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - James Lee (Bird Tail), 1873-1886 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Lewis and Clark County offices, 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - L (correspondents include A.L. Langellier, A. Lavenberg, Lawrence and Martin, T.W. Leighton, John Lepley, J.E. Lippincott, Richard Lockey, L. Loomis, P. Lorillard and Company, A.C. Lux), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - W.T. McFarland (Helena), 1872-1876 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - McLeod and Jack (Helena), 1872-1874 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - Mc (correspondents include David McCranor, John McCune, William McLaughlin, Louis S. McLure, J.H. McRae), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
  - E.G. Maclay and Company (Helena), 1872-1877 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
  - Phil A. Manix (Augusta), 1884-1887 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
  - R.F. May (Blackfeet Agency), 1874 (Box-folder 2 / 26)
  - F.W. Miller (South Fork Sun River; Helena), 1872-1877 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
  - T.F. Morgan (Blackfeet Agency), 1876-1890 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Murphy, Neel and Company (Helena); Murphy, Maclay and Company (Great Falls), 1874-1889 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - M (correspondents include James Machaud, Mansfield and Stickney, George F. Marsh, Nick Millen, George F. Miller, Miller and Addoms, Miller and Rosencrans, H. Milot, J.H. Ming and Company, John E. Morgan, O.H. Morgan, Morris Brothers, John Murphy, P. Murtha), 1872-1889 (Box-folder 3 / 4-5)
  - N-O (correspondents include August Nagel, E. Nebel, H.H. Nelson, R. Bennington Nevitt, W.E. Norris and Brother, Northern Pacific Railroad, Otto Norton [letterhead includes map of Fort Shaw], J.J. O'Connor), 1873-1889 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Henry M. Parchen and Company (Helena), 1873-1880 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Park Hotel (Great Falls), 1887 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - T.C. Power and Brother; T.C. Power and Company, 1871-1889 (Box-folder 3 / 9-17)
  - D.C. Pratt (Wood Camp; Camp Baker), 1873-1878 (Box-folder 3 / 18)
  - P (correspondents include Pacific Glove Works, A. Pambrun, A.H. Peaslee, Peoples National Bank, J.L. Perkins, A.K. Prescott, W.G. Preuitt and Company), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 3 / 19)
  - Q (correspondents include W.J. Quan and Company, William Quinton, E.S. Quigley), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Rich, Willson and Bogert (Bozeman), 1873 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - R (correspondents include Racine Wagon and Carriage Company, J.C. Rainsford, Philip Reade, Reed and Sherwood, W.I. Reed, Rocky Mountain Telegraph Company, Adolph Roenche, H.J. Rosencrans, Charles Rowe, Peter Rush, William Ryan), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
  - Shepherd and Flinn (Cascade), 1888-1889 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
  - Silverman and Cohen (Choteau), 1887-1890 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - George Steell and Company (Sun River), 1876-1883 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - S (correspondents include John Salfinger, San Jose Fruit Packing Company, Wilbur Fisk Sanders, J.B. Sanford, Jacob Schmidt, Schwab and Zimmerman, George W. Smith, Spitzly and Sloan, Stewart and Scott, Benjamin Stickney, Mattie Strong, Granville Stuart, J.T. Sullivan, M. Sweetland, Thomas Switzer), 1871-1889 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - T (correspondents include John B. Taylor, E.J. Thomas, Mrs. R. P. Thoroughman, Robert Tingley, Cris Tillesen, James Travis, John B. Traxler), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - U.S. Army (includes memorandum re liquor on army bases), 1871-1887 (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - U.S. Army (Fort Shaw: includes official letters and orders for goods by soldiers), 1871-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 10-11)
  - U.S. Indian Service; Bureau of Indian Affairs (includes Blackfeet Agency), 1878-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - H.D. Upham (Blackfeet Agency), 1872-1877 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - U (correspondents include William Ulm, Union Republican Congressional Executive Committee, U.S. government agencies), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
  - V (correspondents include Valley Hotel, N. Van Beil, A.R. Van Eman, Peter Van Schaack and Sons, R. Vaughn), 1872-1888 (Box-folder 4 / 15)
  - H.J. Wackerlin and Company (Fort Benton), 1881-1887 (Box-folder 4 / 16)
  - Walter A. Wood Mowing and Reaping Machine Company (Chicago), 1886-1887 (Box-folder 4 / 17)
  - W (correspondents include J.C. Walker and Brother, F.F. Walrath, A.C. Warner, George Warner, O.B. Warwick, Webster and Koontz, A. Weisenhorn, Charles K. Wells, Wells Fargo and Company, D.H. Weston, W.S. Wetzel, George Willard, T.E. Williams, John J. Woods, T.G. Woods), 1872-1890 (Box-folder 4 / 18)
  - Y (correspondents include M. Yurnell, Otto Young and Company, unidentified), 1873, 1890, undated (Box-folder 4 / 19)
  - C-S (correspondents include J.I. Case Threshing Machine Company, John W. Hannay, T.C. Power and Brother, Superior Supply and Fuel Company), 1892-1904 (Box-folder 4 / 20)
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - Letterpress books, 1871-1875 (Box-folder 5 / 1-4)
  - Letterpress books, 1875-1879 (Box-folder 6 / 1-4)
  - Letterpress books, 1879-1882 (Box-folder 7 / 1-4)
  - Letterpress books, 1882-1885 (Box-folder 8 / 1-4)
  - Letterpress books, 1885-1887 (Box-folder 9 / 1-3)
  - Letterpress books, 1887-1889 (Box-folder 10 / 1-3)
  - Letterpress books, 1888-1891 (Box-folder 11 / 1-3)
  - Letterpress books, 1892-1896 (Box-folder 12 / 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1872-1888 (Box-folder 12 / 3)
- Court Papers
  - Joseph H. McKnight Estate payment to attorney; William S. McKnight Estate appointment of administrator; E.A. Carlton vs. Lillie Barker and James Barker re J.H. McKnight stock, 1904-1909 (Box-folder 12 / 4)
- Financial Records
  - Account book (includes payments received for passenger fares at Sun River Station, 1870?; trial balances, 1869-1871; general journal, 1871; inventory, 1878-1884), 1869-1884 (Box-folder 12 / 5)
  - Account with Fort Shaw Restaurant, 1879-1888 (Box-folder 13 / 1-5)
  - Bank statements, 1886-1888, undated (Box-folder 13 / 6)
  - Benton Transportation Company trial balance, 1901 (Box-folder 13 / 7)
  - Bills of lading, 1872-1878 (Box-folder 13 / 8)
  - Cash book, 1871-1877 (Box-folder 13 / 9)
  - Cash books, 1877-1894 (Box-folder 14 / 1-3)
  - Cash books, 1894-1902 (Box-folder 15 / 1-2)
  - Cash memorandum books [3 books], 1887-1894 (Box-folder 15 / 3)
  - Check stub book, 1900-1901 (Box-folder 15 / 4)
  - Daybook: Cutter and Taylor (includes warehouse inventory, 1883-1888), 1869-1871, 1883-1888 (Volume 1)
  - Daybook: "no. 1", 1871 (Box-folder 15 / 5)
  - Daybooks: "no. 2" - "no. 3", 1871-1872 (Box-folder 16 / 1-2)
  - Daybooks: "no. 8" - "no. 12", 1872-1874 (Box-folder 16 / 3-7)
  - Daybooks: "no. 13" - "no. 14", 1874 (Box-folder 17 / 1-2)
  - Daybooks: "no. 16" - "no. 17", 1875-1876 (Volume 2-3)
  - Daybooks: "no. 18" - "no. 19", 1876-1877 (Box-folder 17 / 3-4)
  - Daybooks: "no. 20", 1877-1878 (Box-folder 18 / 1)
  - Daybooks: "no. 21" - "no. 22" [remainder of daybooks overlap with one set being Monday-Wednesday-Friday the other being Tuesday-Thursday-Saturday], 1878-1880 (Volume 4-5)
  - Daybooks: "no. 23", 1878-1880 (Box-folder 18 / 2)
  - Daybooks: "no. 24" - "no. 32", 1879-1885 (Volume 6-14)
  - Daybooks: "no. 35" - "no. 37", 1886-1891 (Volume 15-17)
  - Daybook, 1888 (Box-folder 18 / 3)
  - Daybook: "Great Falls No. 1", 1887-1888 (Volume 18)
  - Daybook: "Blotter No. 2", 1888-1890 (Volume 19)
  - Daybook: "[Blotter] No. 3" "Blotter no.1", 1890-1900 (Volume 20-21)
  - Expense book, 1896-1903 (Box-folder 18 / 4)
  - Grain book, 1888 (Box-folder 18 / 5)
  - Inventory book (includes tax assessment roll for 1878-1888), 1872-1877, 1878-1888 (Box-folder 18 / 6)
  - Inventory book, 1870, 1883-1885 (Box-folder 19 / 1)
  - Invoices, 1873-1874 (Box-folder 19 / 2-3)
  - Invoices, 1875-1880 (Volume 22-23)
  - Invoices, 1881-1885 (Box-folder 19 / 4)
  - Invoices, 1886-1892 (Volume 24-26)
  - Invoices, 1898-1905 (Box-folder 19 / 5-7)
  - Journal: Cutter and Taylor (includes warehouse inventory, March 1886), 1869-1871, 1889 (Volume Vol. 27)
  - Journals, 1871-1889 (Volume Vol. 28-31)
  - Ledgers: Cutter and Taylor, 1869-1871 (Volume Vol. 32-33)
  - Ledger (includes inventory, 1885-1888), 1871, 1885-1888 (Box-folder 19 / 8)
  - Ledger, general and petty, 1871-1874 (Box-folder 20 / 1)
  - Ledger, general, 1874-1884 (Box-folder 20 / 2)
  - Ledgers, general, 1884-1893 (Volume Vol. 34-35)
  - Ledger, petty, 1872-1873 (Box-folder 20 / 3)
  - Ledgers, petty, 1873-1882 (Box-folder 21 / 1-2)
  - Ledger, petty [also includes journal, 1872-1873], 1882-1887, 1872-1873 (Box-folder 21 / 3)
  - Ledgers, petty, 1887-1894 (Box-folder 22 / 1-2)
  - Order books [15 books], 1874-1897, undated (Box-folder 23 / 1-5)
  - Orders, 1872-1877, undated (Box-folder 23 / 6)
  - Payroll; pay table for soldiers, 1895, undated (Box-folder 24 / 1)
  - Price list books [2 books], 1875-1886 (Box-folder 24 / 2)
  - Receipt books: "Benton 1-175" [2 books], 1882-1883 (Box-folder 24 / 3)
  - Receipt book, 1883-1886 (Box-folder 24 / 4)
  - Receipts, 1872-1888, 1903 (Box-folder 24 / 5)
  - Receiving book, 1887-1888 (Box-folder 24 / 6)
  - Rocky Mountain Telegraph Company statements, 1886-1887, undated (Box-folder 24 / 7)
  - Sales books [2 books], 1871-1872 (Box-folder 24 / 8)
  - Saloon ledger (includes inventory, 1874), undated, 1874 (Box-folder 24 / 9)
  - Soldiers' account book (includes warehouse inventory, 1870-1881), 1870-1871, 1870-1881 (Box-folder 25 / 1)
  - Soldiers' account books, 1871-1882 (Box-folder 25 / 2-5)
  - Soldiers' account book, 1882-1888 (Box-folder 26 / 1)
  - Soldiers' blotters, 1872, 1877-1878 (Box-folder 26 / 2-4)
  - Tax receipts, 1884-1902 (Box-folder 26 / 5)
  - "Wagons, Implements, Tent Covers, Building Materials" (includes prices, kinds, weights, etc.), 1888-1894 (Box-folder 26 / 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1872-1898, undated (Box-folder 26 / 7)
- Legal Documents
  - Agreements, 1871-1886 (Box-folder 27 / 1)
  - Bill of sale, 1875 (Box-folder 27 / 2)
  - Contracts, 1871-1880 (Box-folder 27 / 3)
  - Licenses, 1876-1898 (Box-folder 27 / 4)
- Organization
  - Board of trustees' meetings, notices, etc., 1901-1914 (Box-folder 27 / 5)
  - Bylaws, 1894 (Box-folder 27 / 6)
  - Directors' meetings, 1910 (Box-folder 27 / 7)
  - Dividend receipts, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 27 / 8)
  - Minute book, 1894-1909 (Volume Vol. 36)
  - Minutes [removed from minute book], 1894 (Box-folder 27 / 9)
  - Stock certificates, 1894-1909 (Box-folder 27 / 10)
  - Stockholders' ledger and transfer journal, 1894-1911 (Box-folder 27 / 11)
  - Stockholders' meetings, notices, proxies, etc., 1901-1913 (Box-folder 27 / 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1894-1913 (Box-folder 27 / 13)
- Miscellany
  - "Correct table of distances", undated (Box-folder 27 / 14)
  - Freight tariff listing and rules; fabric samples and price lists, 1887, undated (Box-folder 27 / 15)
  - U.S. Army circulars and orders, 1871-1881 (Box-folder 27 / 16)